<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sermons of the ryght famous a[n]d excellent clerke Master Bernardine Ochine, borne within the famous vniversyte of Siena in Italy, nowe also an exyle in this life, for the faythfull testimony of Jesus Christ</title>
            <author>Ochino, Bernardino, 1487-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105735</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841461</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841461</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6046</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08443)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6046)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1322:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sermons of the ryght famous a[n]d excellent clerke Master Bernardine Ochine, borne within the famous vniversyte of Siena in Italy, nowe also an exyle in this life, for the faythfull testimony of Jesus Christ</title>
                  <author>Ochino, Bernardino, 1487-1564.</author>
                  <author>Argentine, Richard, d. 1568.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[62] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Anthony Scoloker. Dwellyng in. S. Nycholas Parryshe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Ippeswych :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1548.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</note>
                  <note>Six sermons, translated by Richard Argentine.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ a(-a1) b-c d⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6046:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6046:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Sermons of the ryght famous a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d excellent clerke Maſter Bernardine Ochine / bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne within the famous vniuerſyte of Siena in Italy / nowe alſo an exyle in this life / for the faythfull teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>¶ Pſal. C. xvij. ¶</bibl> I wyll not dye / but lyue ande declare the workes of the Lorde.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>IMPRINTED</hi> at</hi> Ippeſwych / by Anthony Scoloker. Dwellyng in. S. Nycholas Parryſhe. Anno. 1548.</p>
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum. ¶</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6046:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6046:2"/>
            <head>Vnto The ryght Honourable LORDE Edward / Duke of Somerſet mooſte deare vncle vnto the Kinges Maieſté / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Gouuernour of hys Royall Parſon / and of his Realmes / Dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſubiectes Protectour. Hys graces mooſte humble Seruaunt Rychard Argentyne wiſſheth the increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of honour and grace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>yke as in the beginig (mooſt Gracyous Lorde) it maye appere by the propre names of men / that the ſame were appoynted vnto them by a ſynguler reaſon.
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 4.</note> So by Seth alſo it maye be manifeſt that Kings are geuen vnto the Worlde of God.
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 1.</note> For after the time that the infinite Lorde / had created the vniuerſall worlde / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d reſerued the ſupremité of it vnto him ſelfe / he made man Prince and Lorde / and a Kynge im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly vnder hiouer all / whych myght
<pb facs="tcp:6046:3"/>exerciſe his office / him ſelfe not being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonaly preſent before our eyes / to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we ſhulde alwayes elevate the ſame vnto Heauen there to ſeke him. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of iuſt cauſe Kynges / Prynces ande Gouuernours that mooſt lyuely and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto vs the diuine maieſté of God / being indued with a large porcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame / are called Goddes in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture.
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 6.</note>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 82.</note> And of the prophane poete Homere are named to come from God.</p>
            <p>Theſe Princes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Kinges / as it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the regiſter of thíges done in time / were in mooſt places accuſtumed eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr tender age / to be brought vp vnder iiij. gouuernours. Iuſtice / Prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / For<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude and continency / amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the which vertues. Iuſtice bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the higheſt of power albeit that wyth her manyfold benefittes / neceſſary vnto the vſe of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſhe goeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ground / yet that notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding wyth hyr ſhulders ſhe reacheth vnto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. For as moche as ſhe couereth nothig to hyr ſelfe nor craueth anye thynge / but geueth vnto euery man hys owne / ande reſtoreth euery thynge vnto hys ryght or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre
<pb facs="tcp:6046:3"/>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d kynde.
<note place="margin">Paral. 16.</note> Where therfore the people of God made greate ioye ande feaſted for their true religion reſtored / and were ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the confyrmyng of theyr Kynge / the which dyd miniſter vnto them onely externally iudgement ande iuſtice / what ipye / ought all thys realme to be in / vnto whome it hath fortuned the right ordre of the ſupper of the LORD to be reſtored / through the ſtudye of ſuche a Prynce as walketh in all the waies of God in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d fayth / ledde by a Gouuernour that mooſt parfectly hath trayned hym to the ſame?
<note place="margin">2. Reg. 6.</note>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 25.</note> In whome the ſpirit of Ieſu chriſt that was ones onely offred / manifeſtlye produceth hys effectes.
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> And where as in our daies manye that of right ought to be called martirs / lyke vnto Paule / intendig that Chryſt ſhuld be magnyfyed in theyr bodyes or by theyr death / with theyr blou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / dyd not ſticke to gyue a teſtimony vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worlde of the internal goodnes pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared vnto the ſayntes hereafter / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d fedde the rauening wolues with their carcaſes. Now (God be bleſſed) by our ſo gracyous a Prynce / their teth are blunted and theyr
<pb facs="tcp:6046:4"/>mouthes muſſeled. For thoſe that ſhuld ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve bene the lyght / that the frute of rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes that commeth by Ieſu Chriſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / might have been planted in manye / ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto the Phariſeys that had miracles comune vnto them with the fathers / and the preſence alſo of the mooſt mekeſt lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be of God / the which dyd illuſtrate them wyth hys doctryne ande miracles / wolde in no caſe come to any amendement. And yet they glorye that theyr name was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied to be exerciſed in iuſtice by the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete Eſay.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 60.</note> Where the ixx. interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have (if it be theyr text a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not others) I ſhall gyue thy Princes in peace / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thy Byſſhoppes in iuſtice. But the Hebrewe text (yf they wyll that place to be ment of them and not of other publyke officyers) calleth them more (accordyngly vnto the trueth) exactours or curſitours / nothyng ſeking for the founteine of all ſaturité lac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king the frugalité that Paule willeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vſe. The which thinge they wolde not if they had in them the carefull mynde of the iuſt executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thinges to be done vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Gods honour. Lyke as by the ſhauing
<pb facs="tcp:6046:4"/>of theyr beardes and of theyr heades (the whiche were in the olde tyme tokens of a penſyve ande ſadde minde) they appere to have.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 15.</note> But treuth it is / that lyke as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde (that was accounted to be the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the man) is hatefull vnto them / and is not to be found amongeſt them / ſo is the ſtudye of all good vertue amongeſt others and not amongeſt them. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the migtye LORD hath appointed your grare vnto the ſame office for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of all the faithful / as the neceſſary ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of a Kynge gyve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs by God. And to that purpoſe theſe ſyx Sermons of the famous clerke Bernardinus Ochinus are tranſlated out of the Italyan tongue. The fyrſt declaring what thynge GOD is. The ſecond / Howe to knowe GOD by hys creatures. The thyrd yf Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophye ſerue to true theologye and in wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at maner. Fourthely / Howe we ought to vſe the Scryptures in attayninge the knowledge of GOD. Fyfthly / Of thinconue mences that are happened and dayly happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the abuſe of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Syxtly and finally / If to be good
<pb facs="tcp:6046:5"/>diuines it behoue vs to have the humaine ſciences or not / and geve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto your grace as a mooſt vnworthye gifte / that by your graces fauour the frute of all the oher ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons maye be brought vnto your graces louinge ſervauntes of the whole bodye of this Realme / vnto whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de IESV Chryſt preſerue your grace. At Ippeſwych the xiiij. daye of February. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. M.D. xlviij.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:6046:5"/>
            <head>The preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydereth wher vnto we are created / good Chriſten reader / ſhall fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that of all oure trauay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les thers reſteth no frute / as proueth the holie ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of prophetie by the mouth of Salomon ſaying. I haue loked vppon all the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vnder the ſonne / and haue founde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne other but vanité. Onely reſerued the Image of God in vs / beig the ſpirite that ſuſteineth not the naturall life alone / but alſo all the holie a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vertuous thoughtes / which God hathe created immortal vnto his owne likenes / as thou maieſt weſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue / if thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the ſubſtaunce of the naturall bodie / that hauing the ſpirite / is all liuely / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not onely moueth eche figer / ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / foote / eye and to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue materially / but alſo with the thought / penetrateth the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uens a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in maner co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaueth a ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the immortalité of gods euerlaſtig kigdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tig the ſpirite / teſteth deade pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate of al thoſe vertues / though well thou ſhalt ſe / that it lacketh nether ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / fore / eie
<pb facs="tcp:6046:6"/>tongue nor other membre. Thys I ſaye vnto the (Gentell reader) to thintent th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at thou ſhuldeſt know / that the almightie Creatour is ſerued not of vanityes / that is to ſaye / of bodely or worldly exerciſes / but of ſpirituall thoughtes / which are the iuſt and true ſacrifices vnto God. Ande therby to drawe the to remembre the mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vaile of his workes / ande to thinke more vnto thine ende then to thy life. Diſpoſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thy ſelfe to learne the ſciences that this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle boke ſhall teache the / which treateth of none other but of the ſpirituall thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d beareth in it the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture wich ſo veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reaſons a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo good perſuaſions / that it ſuffiſeth to drawe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thy ſtony harte / and to renewe in the a carnail harte / if thou be one of them / to whome God hath determined to gyve his grace. One of them (I ſaye) that with ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely faith confeſſe Chriſt the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God to haue ſuffred for theyr ſynnes. As the Aucthour hereof ſufficientlye perſuadeth the / who (being a man of great yeres / and wonderfull reputacion) for the love of Chryſt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the trouth / hath rather choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:6046:6"/>exyle and perſecutyon / then con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of wealth / honoures a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d frendſhyp. A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of profou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de learnig. The mooſt notable preacher of all Italy. Famous for the gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>at example of hys good lyfe. Eſtemed and honoured of all Princes / not for his age onely (being a man of lxx yeares / or ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aboutes) but alſo for his infinite vertues a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mooeſte. And finallye ſo beloued of all people / that in what place ſorver he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched / ther hath ever been fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de great prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe of audience. All this notwithſtanding at length (becauſe he ſyncerely followed the true Goſpell / and dyd not ſorbeare to reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the publike abuſes of the romiſh Churche) he was perſecuted of Paule the thyrde / and conſtrayned to forſake Italy / and to flee into Germany Where he hath not ceaſed with his penne / to followe the vertuous exhortacions / that before tyme with hys mouth he preached. Hauynge thereby at this houre (God be thanked) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difyed the mooſt parte of the good vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dings in Italy / in the true and parfect way of Chriſt. To whom with the father a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the holighoſt be prayſe honor a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d glory.</p>
            <p>So be it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6046:7"/>
            <head>Anthony Scoloker vnto the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the multytude of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyous vnder heaven / ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to gether at Kieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem / after that the holy-gooſt was geven vnto the Apoſtles / were ſtonied / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mardayled moche / that they hearde them / ſpeaking every man wyth hys owne ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue / declaring the wonderous doyngs of God / howe moche more then ought we to wonder in theſe our latter dayes / that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve the ſame myracle wrought dayly amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt vs alſo?
<note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> For not only the fathers that were labouring (not many yeres ſynnes) ande travaylinge in thys oure pilgrimage with vs / and now are gone vnto the lyui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g God / do both lyvely and mooſt godly even ſtyll at this daye preache vnto vs / but alſo the very Prophetes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Patriarkes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the whole company that have been eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the worlde / are nowe familiar vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d are become Ingliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Yea / god hi ſelfe of his great infinite
<pb facs="tcp:6046:7"/>mercie in our owne tongue ſpeaketh vnto vs / oute of his mooſt ſacred worde / to our great ioye and ſpirituall comforte. And Paul being a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hebrue borne / hath chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged his tonge / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is become oures / as though he had been bredde and brought vp all the dayes of his lyfe amongeſt vs. Wherfore albeit that the Goſpell beyng nowe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmed / it maye appeare / that myracles at theſe dayes are nothynge ſo neceſſarye as they were in the prymatyue Churche / when by the vertue of the holighooſt and by myracles / that newe doctryne was to be confirmed / yet the verité it ſelf ſheweth the ſame power ſtyll even nowe vnto vs / that ſaid My father worketh eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vntil th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is time / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d I alſo do worke.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> Howe great a wondre therfore is it that almoſt no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth marvail at / to ſee that by the meanes of thigs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to writtig two / though one be never ſo farre diſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other / may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate their ſecrets tegether? a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yet paſſig this / by the helpe of the ſame / we receave the v<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>tuous cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels / the mooſt ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly inſtruerio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the godly prechigs of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers (as they called the prophetes: becauſe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the maieſté of the aet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rnall god they did ſee
<note place="margin">1. Reg. 2.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:6046:8"/>as it had been in a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ece microur / the ſecret miſteryes of thinges both paſt and for to com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) and yet we mardall nothing at all. But God (not leauyng vs thus / where as by the very true monuments of the godly that are paſſed from vs / theyr mindes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eft with vs ſtill / we are urle or nothig amended) doth ſende vnto vs hys Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes oute of ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge countreis / that the congregation therby maye be edifyed / and mooſt bounde to render thankes vnto hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his infinite mercy.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> Amongeſt the wh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich Bernardinus Ochinus and Petrus Martyr men of great learninge / whiche are nowe come vnto vs. And for as moch as the ſayd Bernard preachech in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talyan tongue which all men vnderſtand not / I have ſeth forth ſyx of his Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s oute of this tongue into Inglyſh. Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to ſet forth the reſt very ſhortlye (yf theſe ſhalbe thankefully receaued) to the intent that his nature tongue therby may be made oures / and that the glory of God maye the better be ſet forth. Vnto whom all honour is due / world wythourende.</p>
            <p>So be it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermons">
            <pb facs="tcp:6046:8"/>
            <head>Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Maſter Bernar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyne Othyne / borne wythin the famous vniverſite of Siena in Italy / nowe aſo an ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le in this lyfe / for the faithfull teſtimony of Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <head>Sermo i. Vhat thinge God is.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Gnoraunce ſpecyallye of the heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly things / is the greateſt lack that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be in man and aboue all other the ignoraunce or lack of knowledge of God. For as it is impoſſible to attaine the ſcience of Philoſophye Aſtrologie Geometrye or of any other lyke / without the grounde or fyrſt pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipailes. So without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God the true beginnyng and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cypall of true deuynite it is impoſſible to have any lyght of the trouth / neceſſary a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:6046:9"/>proffitable to the ghoſtly health. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe / as the knowledge of the firſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palles of one ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the knowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of all the trouth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that that ſcience conteineth. So of the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God / depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the knowledge of all the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtaunces a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d trouth of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie or Deuinité Wherfore ſeing howe moche peſtiferous and deteſtable the igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunce of God is / and howe moche neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie the true knowledge of him is / I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thought it expedient / fyrſt to conſyder what thinge God is.</p>
               <p>It is a mooſt eaſye thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to knowe that God is / or that there is a god / ſithens that there is no Nation ſo barbarous / but that it beleueth that there is a God / being a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall knowledge that God hath ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in the hartes of al men / that if the man haue any iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at all / it behoueth him with the harte to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that there is a God. For albeit there haue bene many wicked whiche with their mouthes haue ſayde / there is no God. Neuertheles the ſelf ſame / when they haue fallen into any peril or neceſſité / haue been e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forced of that
<pb facs="tcp:6046:9"/>onely light and religion of God / to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende them ſelues vnto him / ſo that we muſt of force repute hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a very ydeote / that demeth God.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 13.</note> Ande being therfore an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and eaſy thinge to endwe that there is a God / we moſt nowe travaile a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor (though it be mooſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>) to knowe what that god is. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> haue bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it is impoſſible that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhulde I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magin what God is becauſe infinitene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all propor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> exced<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenes of our vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> / ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es are drowned in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die / occupied of fan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the derke vaynes of thinges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> / far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of from God. We be weake of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and impole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t through the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and our owne ſynnes. Wherefore they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye that we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue noue other knowledg of God / but the negatiue / that is to witte / we maye knowe that God is not materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all nor forme imperfect nor yet ſoule of the world / that he is not Earth / Water / Ayre / Fyre / Winde / ſeecre / Mons / Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / Corporall light nor any vertue ſpred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de abroade. He is not the beaultie that we ſee / the ſwetenes that we taſte / nor other
<pb facs="tcp:6046:10"/>thinge ſenſible / imaginable or intelligible of vs / but that infinitely he exceadeth all creatures / and all things that we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. In him ther is an inacceſſible lyght ſuch as they / which with theyr thoughtes in maner have been rayſed ſo hyghe / that they have founde what God is have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceued them ſelves.
<note place="margin">Tim. 6.</note> And they who ymagin in theyr myndes to have founde God / do fabricate an ydoll / oute of all meaſure diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunt from the true beyng of God / as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by his commaundemente to the Iewes / whan he prohibited the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſculp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or grauinge of ydolles / vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng not of the materyall ydolles onely / but alſo of the imaginable.
<note place="margin">Erod. 20.</note> For our wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are extreme darknes / in comparyſon of gods ineſtimable fyrſt light. So that it behoueth vs with Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to enter in Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Sanctorum and with Moſes into the Celeſtiall Clowde / if we will knowe / that is to ſay / to knowe that we knowe not / in ſo the wyſe that the more fervently a man will profeſſe not to knowe ſomoch the bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter he doth knowe / and who preſumeth to knowe / is fartheſt of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the knowledge.
<pb facs="tcp:6046:10"/>And why? becauſe God in his power and lyght ſtandeth ſo hidde in darkenes from vs / that with blindnes we ſee him / wyth ignoraunce we knowe him / with retuing or with going backe we comprehend him / in fleing we finde him and with ſcylence we prayſe him.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1</note> And it behoueth him that will knowe what thinge God is / to ſtudy in the ſcole of ſimpliene and reſt vanquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of that ineſtimable / inacceſſible ande incomprehenſible lyght.</p>
               <p>And I confeſſe that we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend God / in ſuch maner as God compre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hendeth him ſelfe. That is to ſaye / we can not have a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infinite knowledge of him / as do the bleſſed ſaintes that is to ſaye / to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve as they have the clere naked / open and viſible ſight of him / to beholde hym in the founteyne of his bryghtnes / face to face in the verye being that he is.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2</note> But we may very well attaine a knowledge what God is though not ſo perfectly as we ſhall kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we in the other lyte. For it is not poſſible we ſhuld knowe what thig God is not / if fyrſt we learne not to knowe what thing he is / and that his being is ſo pertect that
<pb facs="tcp:6046:11"/>it repugneth thimperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that be not. Wherfore conſidering all the negatiues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are rehearſed of god a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re grounded vppon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> poſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> / we muſt ſaye of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God more perfertly / in knowing that is to be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / then in knowing nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at all. And therfore ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king of more h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e knowledge affyrma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue / that in this preſent lyfe the electe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munly and without ſpeciall priuiledge a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d miracle had of God / I ſaie / that fyrſt thou oughteſt to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder that the creature hath hys beyng / although imperfect. Ande God hath his being without anie imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Yea his beyng is infinitely perfect. wherfore to knowe what thinge God is / it behoueth the to do as he doth that wyll make an Image. Fyrſt he cutteth of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny peces / before he parforme the forme that he deforeth / and afterwardes payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech and apparcelleth it.</p>
               <p>So is it neceſſarie that with the minde / thou thou fyrſt conſyder the beyng of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Ande becauſe thou ſhalt fynde hym
<pb facs="tcp:6046:11"/>repleate of iperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / beynge terminable create / temporall / corruptyble and other lyke / therfore it behoueth the to clenſe / pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryfye and take from him all thoſe imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectyons / and ymagyn him infinite / inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minable / icorruptible a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in effect abſtract and lyfte vp aboue all imperfectyon. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth that ſuffiſe / but alſo it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye that thou floryſhe ande adorne him of all perfectyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſſyble / in ſoche wyſe th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at thou conceaue to ſee him aeterne / neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary / ſimple immutable a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d infinite. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet doth all that ſuffiſe / but morouer it behoueth the with thy thought to puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d clenſe of all i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perfectyon the Wyll a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mynde created / the wyſdome created the iuſtice bountye / pitye / power / Charitye / treuth / beaultye and all the other vertues a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d perfections / to which imperfectyon is contrarye / ande conſequently to entythe hym of infynyte degrees of perfectyon / ande ſo to beholde hym in God as a thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge puryfyed / to be vnto him / dyvyne ande intynite. B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T becauſe thoſe powers / vertues and operatyons with imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in maner ruleth in vs / will not ſuffer
<pb facs="tcp:6046:12"/>our wittes to conceaue that creature in his beyng and to clenſe and ſpoile h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m of all imperfectyons / and ſo to make him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite / we can not in our beyng ſee him in God in whome there can be nothing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but it muſt ſuffiſe vs to ſee hym in vertue and eminencie. So that albeit in gods propre beyng ther is the corporall vyſyon / the imaginatyon / credulyte opini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on / diſcourſes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d other actions eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Nevertheles it muſt ſuffiſe vs to ſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vertue and eminencye. For to ſee God clerely / it includeth and conteyneth all per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection / lyke as the golde conteyneth the perfection of all other metalles. He then that ſeeth that diuine being wyth all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectyon poſſible / ſeeth what thing God is / becauſe he ſeeth a ſpirituall lyght / mooſt pure mooſt clere / mooſt ſimple and exel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently fayre / aeterne / immutable / neceſſary and infinitely perfect / replete of Celeſtiall faelicite / iuſtice / powr / bountie / verite / wiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome / mercye / charite and of all the other perfect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vertues infinitely parfect and that in it / in vertue and eminencye be all the colours / odours / ſauours / ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des / 
<pb facs="tcp:6046:12"/>ſonges / ſwetenes / fairenes / honours / dig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nityes / treaſures / pleaſures and faelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the woorld / infinitely a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d without proporcyon / more perfect then they be of them ſelues here.</p>
               <p>And moreouer it behoueth the to kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we that the beyng of the creature is a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe and a mooſt fleyght vanité in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of Gods beyng / and the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce more / then is betwene our ſhadowe ande our ſelues.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> It is to be ſayde of God / that ſurely he is onely the thinge that is. Lyke wiſe I ſay of our powers / beaulte trueth / charité / iuſtice / wyſdome and of all our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues / that compared to the diuine they be as mooſt vaine Images / and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes / infinitely diſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them of god.
<note place="margin">Iohan. 5.</note> Alſo it behoueth to knowe / that God is not ydell / but that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually worketh (as Chriſt ſaith) in ſuch wiſe / that he hath not onely geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the worlde his beige / but alſo continuallye conſerueth all the thinges created / and all the vertues / that of all the myracles and ſtraunge effectes / we konwledge only God to be Aucthour and to him we gyue all thankes honor a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:6046:13"/>glorie. So likewiſe ought we to knowled<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of him all the naturall effectes and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racions / and not to extolle or praiſe natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / but God onely / who grueth and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the bring ande vertue to all thinges. Neither ought there any other chaunce or fortune to be named / but all to be confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of God / and he onely to be thanked / e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as he continually worketh for vs.</p>
               <p>And as his power is neuer ydell / but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall working in all creatures. So his wiſdome continually ſeeth / diſpoſeth and ordeineth all thinges mooſt beſt / and his bountie likewiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnto vs his benefyttes and graces.</p>
               <p>Furthermore it is neceſſarie thou knowe that all that god hath wrought / worketh or ſhall worke in his creatures / is all for man / for whome they be created and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. For all the giftes ande benefittes that from the beginning haue bene made or ſhalbe made to the creatures / Man is bounde to knowledge them as made to hym / and accordingly therfore to thanke God. Ande eſpecially the choſen or electe / to whome all creatures do ſerue / both the
<pb facs="tcp:6046:13"/>predeſtinate and reprobate.
<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Yea the Ann<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles and the deuelies / euen to the very ſines. And becauſe God doth here mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and diſcouer him ſelfe / with his omni potent wiſdome / trueth / iuſtice / bountie and his other vertues ande perfections / not onely in his creatures / but moch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in his ſcriptures / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſpecially in Chriſt on the croſſe / chefely to them that by faith conceaue him with ſpirite. Therfore it behoueth him that will knowe what this GOD is / to beholde him particulerly in Chriſte / and to beſeche him to giue him ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely ande clere light to knowe him not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely in his creatures and ſcriptures / but ſpecially in Chriſte crucifyed / to thende that in him a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by him / vnderſtanding the great bountie of God / we maye ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre vnto hym all honour and glory / by our Sauiour Ieſu Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:6046:14"/>
               <head>Section. ij. Howe to knowe God by hys creatures.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD in his maieſté apparelled with his perfections / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the well of his brightnes (as ſayth Paule) is a certaine light inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſyble and hidde.
<note place="margin">1. Tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> But here he ſomwhat diſcouereth him ſelf by his creatures / as who will entre into Rome / muſt of force knowe by the pyllers / ſepultures / Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ande by the great ruines that he ſhall fynde there / that the Romaines in times paſt / haue been of great power / dominion and wiſdome.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 15.</note> So he which entereth into this worlde / ſeing this great engine / muſt of force knowe the maker therof to be the God omnipotent. And beholding the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre of his creatures / muſt not onely ſee but alſo maruell at the wiſdome of God.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.3.</note> And wyth Dauid crye and ſaye. Lorde thou haſt created all thinges in wiſdome. Ande moreouer it behoueth hym to ſaye that GOD is beſt / ſeyng that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally he diſpoſeth newe gyftes vnto hys creatures. And ſeyng that by due meanes
<pb facs="tcp:6046:14"/>he leadeth them to theyr ende / he is forced to confeſſe GODS deuine prouidence / ande ſo in concluſion by the thinges crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted / to come to the knowledge of GOD / and of all his perfections / as farre forth as they appeare in his creatures / and that becauſe the creatures be vnyted ſo to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that eche one hangeth on other / and all of GOD / in ſoche wiſe that they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a ladder to the vnderſtandinge of the naturall / by the whyche they clyme ande aſcende euen to GOD. They ſee that this inferiour worlde / is gouuerned of the heauens / ande that the heauens kepe theyr courſes vniformely / by continuall mouing / and therof be conſtrayned to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyder / that the vertue whiche moueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / beyng infaticable ande neuer wery / is ſpirituall / for if it were corporall / it ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ende or at the leaſt waxe weake. Ande ſo goyng farther / they conſyder that that ſpirituall vertue / not being the ſupreame / is gouuerned by an other. Ande becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe they can not attayne the infynite euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtinge / they are forced to come to a fyrſt ſupream<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> intelligence / the whiche moueth
<pb facs="tcp:6046:15"/>without being moued / and to a fyrſt cauſe independent / ande ſo they aſcend to the knowledge of GOD. Moreouer / by the beaulté of the creatures / they aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the knowledge of the beaulté of God. By the ordre / Armonie and conſent that appeare in the creatures / they attaine the conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Gods infinite ſapience or wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.
<note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note> Ande ſo by the viſyble workes of God (to the regarde wherof Dauid cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs / ſayinge Come ande beholde the workes of the lorde) they attaine to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyder the inuiſyble perfections of God / his euerlaſting power ande Diuinité as Paule wryteth.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> There is no creature ſo bace nor ſo vyle / in whome there ſhineth not the glory of God / in which thou maiſt ſee hys greate power / wyſdome / bounté beaulté and the other perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And by howe moche the creatures be more noble / hyghe / worthie and excellent / by ſo moche the more do they diſcouer God.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.</note> Lyke as the heauens which particulerly do ſhewe the glory of God. And the more perfectly we knowe the creatures Yea God in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſo moche the more we ryſe to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:6046:15"/>of God / ande by ſo moche the more our vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges wholy a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with perfect light is vnited and copulate vnto hym.</p>
               <p>It is true that many conſyder the creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues / without reſpect to hym that hath created them / ande ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerueth and gouuerneth them. But thoſe are of more groſſe condicion then is the owle / which / becauſe he can not beholde the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / forceth him ſelf and taketh pleaſure to beholde hym in the ſterres. And they / not ſeing God in his glorie / ſeke not / at the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſe wiſe / to ſee him in the mirrour of hys creatures.</p>
               <p>But knowe thou fyrſt that this ladder of the creatures to clime vnto God is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous / becauſe that God hauing put in them a certeine beaultie and ſwerenes / to thende that mannes vnderſtandinge of the taſte of the ſwete running water ſhuld be prouoked to ſeke the fonteine or ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d therby to ſeke God with more vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie. Many ſtaye or rather fyre them ſelues in the degrees / ande neuer arriue to the heigth.</p>
               <p>And ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of the ſight of the beaulté crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:6046:16"/>/ fall into vyle / baſe / vnclene and fylthy thoughtes. And other ſwelle in pryde of that theyr vayne ſcience / without climing to taſte the ſwetenes of Gods bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie / fyxe them ſelues in the degrees / and there ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we them ſelues contented for rewarde to be ſeen and reputed for learned / of the blin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de folyſh and frantyke woorlde.</p>
               <p>Furthermore / this ladder is very hard and imperfect becauſe that by the ſynne of our fyrſt parentes we are ſo blynded of ſight / that wyth great difficulté we maye ſee god in the darkenes of things created / ſpecyally becauſe the wiſe of the woorlde / coueting to ſearch all the properties / ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tues and qualyties of the creatures / have entangled them ſelves with their curious thoughtes to the vayne ſhadowes of the worlde / that fyrſt they are attrapped of death or ever they are a lytle elevated their mindes towardes God.</p>
               <p>It is alſo a very longe ladder / for the great diſtaunce that is betwene the lowe ſenſyble creatures (at the which / as at the fyrſt ſteppe or degree it behoueth to begin at to elyme) and God. For it requireth ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treme
<pb facs="tcp:6046:16"/>labour to arryſe to the knowledge of the material ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d moch more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to clime with the thought to the kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wledge of the imateriall. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou art arrived at the perfet knouledge of the ſupreame creature / becauſe betwene that and God there is infinite dyſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / before that with the thought thou arrive at god / thy wittes ſhalbe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maner ſo wekened th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at in the ende thou ſhalt attayne none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but a weake inparfect and darke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</p>
               <p>Therfore to have ſufficiente lyght of God to the knowledge of him by the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures / ſuffiſeth not to our ſaluatyon.</p>
               <p>For though with all naturall lyght we dyd arryve by the creatures at the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God / yet can we be none other but good Metaphiſici or natural theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giens / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not therfore good a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall diuines / becauſe the woorlde ſhuld allwayes haue more operatyon in vs and in our hertes then God. We myght well leave our goods for pleaſure / ande one an other for honour / as in tymes paſt certei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Phyloſophers have done / whyche left
<pb facs="tcp:6046:17"/>one vice perceauing other. But no man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> willinglie forſake the world / him ſelfe and all thinge / and haue God for God / and for his onely laſte ende / but he alone to who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the bountie of God is diſcouered / in ſoche wyſe that he maye more in him / then all the richeſſes / pleaſures and dignities of the worlde. Wherunto ſuffyſeth not the bountie of God diſcouered in his crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures / nor all our naturall light / as Paul writeth to the Romaines.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 1.</note> Whome he ſhe wech that the naturall light / whiche lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the knowledge of god by the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures / was not ynough / becauſe thereof they had not light to glorifye nor yelde the due thankes vnto GOD.</p>
               <p>wherfore they are not to be excuſed whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che / thinking the naturall light to ſuffyſe / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d truſting in their propre forces or ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes / demaunde none other light of God / but are to be reputed wicked. For as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as we all haue nede of the deuine gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and lyght to knowe GOD ſuffycient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Neyther is it ynough to beholde hym in his creatures. But it behoueth wyth the ſpirite and ſupernaturall lyght to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb facs="tcp:6046:17"/>hym in Chriſte / where he diſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth hym ſelfe with ſo greate exceſſyue bountie / that he rauiſſheth ande draweth vnto him the hartes / in ſoche wyſe / that deliuering them of the worlde / he ſaueth them. Let vs therfore fyxe our eyes in that diuine ſpectacle / to thende / that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in him and by hym the bountie of the father / we maye rendre vnto him all honour a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d glorie by our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſu chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sermon">
               <head>Sermon. iij. If Phyloſophie ſerue to true Theologie or diuinite / and in what maner.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me the which deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing al ſupernatural light / thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke that in the worlde there is no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne other Theology or diuinité but the naturall / whiche they call Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſyca. And becauſe that a Man can not be a Good Metaphyſiens / vnles
<pb facs="tcp:6046:18"/>he be fyrſt a good Philoſopher / therfore they be conſtrained to ſaie / that Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie ſerueth to Theologie or Diuinite. Somme other / not being able to denye Theologie or diuinitie to be ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall / ſaye that it is grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vppon the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall / in ſuch wiſe that (after their ſayig) as the knowledge intellectiue requireth the ſenſytiue / becauſe therof it hath origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall / groweth and hangeth or dependeth / ſo hath Theologie or diuinitie nede of Philoſophie / becauſe of it it taketh begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning groweth and is eſtabliſſhed.</p>
               <p>Philoſophy then after theyr opinion / is the guide that leadeth vnto Santa Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torum / to beholde the celeſtiall thinges.</p>
               <p>The ladder by the whiche it behoueth / to clime to true Theologie or diuinitie. And mannes reaſon is the rule to the whiche (according to theyr iudgementes) reſorte all the knowledge of the diuine light. And in ſo moch do they allowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / in as moch as they agre / not with the holy ſcriptures nor with the ſpirite / but with theyr blinde humaine iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / which they holde for the ſceptre that ſhe with all / euen to God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6046:18"/>But I ſaye / that as our humaine reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſinne of our fyrſt pareutes / is wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / blinde / frenetike and fooliſh. So is ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewiſe theyr Philoſophie. Ande that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that albeit after the ſynne / God left vnto man a litle light of the naturall thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / neceſſarie to the humaine life and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to our miſerable ſtate. Man ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles / in whome reſteth a certeyn pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and curioſyte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / wolde not content hym ſelf with ſo ſymple a knowledge. As whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a certeyn Philoſopher / geuing him ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe thurtye yeres to ſtudye the knowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of all the properties of the bee / coulde never perfectly attaine his deſyre. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue geuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to ſearch the knowledge of al the properties / qualities / vertues and operations of euerie ſenſyble thing ande not onely of the baſe ande cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptyble but alſo of the celeſtiall bodyes. Yea (and which is more) they haue enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſed to ſpeake of the Soule / of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles / of God and of the thinges ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall / In ſoche wyſe that (paſſyng the lymytes of theyr ſmall light / and walking blyndely) eche one hathe fabrycate in hys
<pb facs="tcp:6046:19"/>minde his owne fantaſie / and to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe have ſo ſpoken and written every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne according to his propre freneſye / wher of is growe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo great varieté of opinions / ſo many confuſions / errours / ſectes ande hereſies / that (as ſaint Ierome iuſtly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them) the Philoſophers are the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryarkes of the heretykes / ande the fyrſt begotten of Egipte. Ande it is an olde prouerbe / a great Philoſopher a great he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retyke.</p>
               <p>The naturall reaſon therfore / that is not healed by faith / is frenetyke and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh / as thou mayeſt well thinke when th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou conſidereſt the preſumptyon / in that it pretendeth to be the guyde / fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacyon ande ladder of the diuine knowledges. Where as it ſerueth not to rayſe the man to the knowledge of God / but moche leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe geueth him cauſe to confeſſe with So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates that not only he knoweth not / but alſo that / wythout the diuine grace he can do nothinge. Albeit that that Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophye is nowe ſo proude / that with the ſuppreſſinge and perſecutinge of Chryſt / the Goſpell / the grace ande fayth / it hath
<pb facs="tcp:6046:19"/>alwayes magnifyed the carnall man / his lyght ande his powers / And is become ſo frenetike / that oneles it be healed by faith / it wyll beleue nothing to be true / but that it thinketh good / neyther is it poſſible to perſuade him in any treuth / yf fyrſt decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vnto him by his frenetyke reaſons / it be not conformable to hys blynde iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Conclude therfore / that Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phye lyeth lowe in the darke vale of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandyng / and can not lyft the head to the hygh ande ſupernaturall thynges / in reſpect wherof / it is vtterly blynde / ande knoweth not / neyther by experience nor reuelation / ſo that in it / it is impoſſible to eſtablyſh the foundacion of the faith. For as the feling paſſeth not the region of the ſenſible thinges. So likewiſe can nothne mayne reaſon nor phyioſophye paſſe the regyon of the naturall thynges. The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man (as wryteth Paule) vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth not the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges of the ſpirite. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not capax / that is percea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth it not / he mocketh a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſcorneth it. Yea he per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecuteth / baniſheth withſtandeth / denyeth ande repugneth the myracles / reuelatids
<pb facs="tcp:6046:20"/>propheties / the grace fayth the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures / God / Chryſt and hys membres.
<note place="margin">Iohe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 10.</note> Yf they heare the Goſpell preached of a faithfull man / they ſaye he is madde / fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous or poſſeſſed of the deuell / as was ſayde of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Warr. 8.</note> If of a learned man / they ſaye his great ſtudye hath brought hym oute of hys wyttes / whyche alſo was lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to Paule.
<note place="margin">Act. 7.</note> If of an ignorant / howe / ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye they can he be learned that neuer ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed letters? And if of a poore wretche (as touchinge the worlde) they ſaye to hym as was ſaied to the boren blinde man. Thou waſt borne in ſynne / and wilt thou teache me?
<note place="margin">Iohan. 9</note> And ſo in effect can in no wyſe abyde to heare the thinges of God. Go reade the holy ſcriptures / ande thou ſhalt fynde that the carnall wyſdome ande humayne reaſon hath alwaies rebelled agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt God. She is the ſame that / fygured by the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent / perſuaded our fyrſt parentes to taſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of the prohibited apple / ande that bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not the worde of God / and that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes taught them to excuſe them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. That made Caim to ſlea his brother Abell / ande that perſuaded the worlde in
<pb facs="tcp:6046:20"/>the time of Noe / that the generall diluge or floude ſhulde not come. She cauſed the building of the towre of Babel. She pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked Pharao to reſyſt God. She indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the people of God to murmur againſt him / and to worſhip the golden calſe / and mouéd the Gentiles to ydolatrie. It is that harlott that made Salomon / looſe hys wittes / and ſtirred his Father to kyll Vria. And finallie / ſhe is the ſame that per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecuted the Patriarckes / Prophetes / A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Martirs / and ſainctes of the old and newe Teſtament. Beholde whether ſhe be a wycked foole or not that putte Chriſt on the croſſe / and where as Chriſte crucified is the right wiſdome of God ſhe accounteth it for a mere madnes. Surely there is nothing that hath ſo moch fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the kingdom of Antechriſt as ſhe / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che hath introduced all the ſuperſticions / Hypocriſies. Ydolatries and euelles that haue been committed vnder colour of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes. The faith hath not had a greater ennemy then ſhe. The Church of Chriſte was a Paradiſe whiles the ſymple fayth reigned. But taking in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the Scepter
<pb facs="tcp:6046:21"/>of humaine reaſon / it is become a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Babylon. And where as the clere / ſure and infallyble faith / by geuing light of the trueth / magnifyeng Chriſte / his grace a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the goſpell / doth aonichilate or bringe to nought the fleſhly man / ande maketh the parſon ſymple / pure / immaculate / vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d houe. The darke / blinde deceitfull freenetike fooliſh and hereticall carnall rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon / wyſdome and Philoſophie / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d oppreſſeth the trueth. And to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ande extolle the errours perſecuteth / crucifieth and burieth Chriſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grace a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the goſpell a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d magnifieth the caruall ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euen to the heauen. All the harlots to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue not ſo moch corrupted the worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de as this onely carnall reaſon / prudence and ſalſe Philoſophie. No nor the ſymple ignoraunce hath not ſo moche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſed the worlde as the humaine ſcience / wiſdome and Philoſophi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> / which maketh men bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / vnſhamefaſt / hoote / l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers / proude / con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencious / frenetike foolyſh and wicked. Wherfore Paul exhorted the Coloſſians to beware of her deceypt / becauſe (as God ſayth by the Prophet Eſaye) ſhe begyleth
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 47.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6046:21"/>the parſons. For the wyſe or the worlde be the mooſt deceaued / mooſt fooles / moſt wicked and mooſt contrarie to Chriſte. And it requireth a ſpeciall miracle to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Reade the Chriſtian hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories / and thou ſhalt fynde that thoſe be they which euermore haue been the fyrſt to perſecute the Goſpell. And they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wycked and fooliſh that will grounde Chriſt vppon Ariſtotell / euen like vnto them that will buylde a Towre vppon a wheaten ſtrawe. Chriſt and not the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie is the onely true fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his Churche and of the true ſupernaturall di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinitie of the which he is the onely work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter / and not Ariſtotell. I praye the what hath Ariſtotle to do wyth Chriſte? Manie haue enforced them ſelues to agre Ariſtotle with Plato / but they coulde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bringe it to paſſe / becauſe Ariſtotle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at the loweſt of the ſenſible thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / ryſeth in the ende to as high as maye be. And Plato begineth where as Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre nowe howe it is poſſible to agre hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with chriſt / though many will make hym a piller of the Goſpell a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:6046:22"/>to clime to heauen. Let vs therfore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the ſciences of the worlde as vaine / bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g like vnto the harlots / that with their flattering woordes and falſe deceipts cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the mindes. And let vs conſider that if the prieſtes of the old Teſtament were prohibited to take a comune woman for a wife / howe much more the Chriſtian that is all wholy conſecrate ande dedicate to God / ought to flee and eſchewe the vayne ſciences and onely ſeruing him ſelf of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as of mooſt vile handmaidens / to knitte hym ſelue in ſpirite and with harte ande minde to applie him ſelfe to that pure and immaculate virgin of the holy Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie or diuinité? To the intent that euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly we maye render to God all laude honour and glory / by our Sauiour Ieſu Chriſte. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:6046:22"/>
               <head>Sermon. iiij. Howe we ought to vſe the holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / in attaining the knowledge of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He knowledge of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures is not ynough to proue that we haue ſuffycient light of God / becauſe it is poſſible that a man maye by his pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte memorie attaine the holy ſcriptures ande their interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions in his minde / and by force of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall wytte / naturally vnderſtand them / and be neuertheles for all that without faith / ſpirite and lyuely light of God.
<note place="margin">Lue: 24.</note> For therto it behoueth hym to haue the ſpirite and ſupernaturall light / that God with his fauour do open a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d penetrate the min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de by his diuine grace. So that therfore we muſt not accompte the holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res for our laſt ende / or for our ſupreame Quene or Empereſſe / but for meanes that ſerue to the faith / to the ſpirite ande to the true knowledge of God / muche more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the creatures. And we ought to ſerue our ſelues of them in diuers wayes / for that they firſt incite and teach vs to repaire to
<pb facs="tcp:6046:23"/>God / ſayinge / in him is the chief bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>té / go to him / for he is faithfull / and hath promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed to make you taſte all vertue and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in him. Yea. though they do not make the liuely to knowe God / yet worke they / as the Samaritane did / that ſent the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritanes to Chriſt / who otherwiſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de them taſte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d feele that which the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritane had ſaid of him vnto them / in ſoche wiſe that when they returned / they confeſſed / ſaying we beleued not at all by thy wordes / we our ſelues haue hearde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d knowe / that this is truly the ſauiour of the worlde.
<note place="margin">John. 5.</note> And ſo the holy ſcriptures do ſend the to chriſte / to the ende that he maye ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy hart / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d make the i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpirite liuely to vnderſtande that which already thou haſt redde in the dead letter / that thou maiſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye vnto the ſcriptures / we neuer beleued by thy wordes / the which / being without ſpirite / coulde not make vs taſte liuely the great bounté of God. It is true that by thy wordes we haue bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prouoked to go to Chriſte / who / ſpeaking vnto vs in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hath made vs to fele in the harte / a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re clere / high and diuine effect of that thou
<pb facs="tcp:6046:23"/>haſt ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They erre therfore that / fedig them ſelues of the letter a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not of the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite / do fixe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in the holy ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſeke none other light but that. Yea I ſaye that for one houres ſtudie / they ought to praie a thouſand / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of god the true vnderſtanding of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And like as the Placoniſtes helde opinion / that the ſenſyble thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges geueth vs occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtudie in the booke of the minde in whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che (they ſaye) is imprynted all the very<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>té. So muſt we conſyder that the holye ſcriptures do call vs to Chriſt / in whome (as Pauſe ſayth) be hidde all the treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of wyſdome and knowledge. This is no leſſe then true / that lyke as if thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt a frende whome thou haſt not tryed (though alwayes thou haſt trauayled to proue hym) thou woldeſt not inwardely knowe hym for a frende (though he were euer in thine eye) becauſe the profe hath not rooted hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thy minde. So albeit the holy ſcriptures do call ande exhorte the to ſeke god in ſpirite / it is yet impoſſible that thou ſhuldeſt finde god i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trueth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures / if firſt by ſpirite / thou haue him not at the harte.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6046:24"/>They ſerue alſo an other maner / that many tymes happeneth. As where God maketh the in ſpirite with lyuely faith to feale a deuine trueth. Afterwardes / redi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the holy ſcriptures / thou findeſt that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that thou haſt ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued. And therof reſting contented / thou confirmeſt thy ſelf in the fayth of that trueth / not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that it ought to ſuffiſe the / of the fyrſt inſpiration of the holighoſt. And ſo moreouer becauſe that in Chriſt is the ende of the lawe / all the promiſſes fulfyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all the prophecies verified / the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes / figures a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſcriptures of the olde Teſtament / he that redeth it and ſeeth all fulfylled in chriſt is forced to ſatiſfye him ſelf of the trueth / and to eſtabliſh him ſelf in faith.
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> For Chriſt ſent the Iewes (that wold not beleue hym) to the holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / as to them that witneſſed of hym. Afterwardes / albeit that in the Churche of God / to be ſatiſfyed / grounded a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſſhed in the diuine / celeſtiall and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall verité / it behoueth in effect to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to the inwarde wytnes of the holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghooſt / without whome we can not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we
<pb facs="tcp:6046:24"/>whiche ſcriptures of god be holy and whiche not. Neuertheles / after that by ſpirite we are aſſured that our holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures be of God / we ought to ſerue our ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues of them as of a certeine infailyble a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſupreame outwarde rule to teache / repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende / correct and exhort the others ande to conumce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſpeake againſt it. For (as Paule writeth) amongeſt the extery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our thinges we haue not a more ſure cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / parfect a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtedfaſt rule / then this / with whiche we ought in ſpyrite to rule all our wordes / workes / dedes and lyfe.
<note place="margin">2. Tmo. 3.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The holy ſcriptures moreouer ſhewe vnto vs (though farre of) our countrey. By her we haue lyght of God of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo of his threateninges.
<note place="margin">Roma. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> And they nouriſh in vs / the faith hope / charité feare and other vertues. They comforte vs in our troubles / and in proſperite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte vs to be temperate. They diſcouer the vanities of the world / our miſeries a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the bountie of God. And who that ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them muſt of forie recyre or withdra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we him ſelf from the worldly thoughtes / and ſettle his minde to mortifie his vices / 
<pb facs="tcp:6046:25"/>inordinate deſires and affections. So that the ſtudie of them is very proffitable to them that duely vſe it. But it behoueth not to ſtudie as the Iewe (who fyxeth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the vttermuſt rynde of the letter / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che) as Paule ſaith) killeth / and beholding Moſes wyth the face couered / ande not entering into Sancta Sanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but as the true Chriſtian / to whome is geuen the knowledge of GODS celeſtiall Reyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne or Kingdome / without parables / that with the lyuely ſpyrite doth penetrate to the lyuelie taſte ande fealing of GOD in Chriſt / beholding hym with lyuely faith in the face diſcouered / ande entryng into Sancta Sanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / to ſee wyth clere ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall lyght / the hygh reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſecretes of God. To who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all laude / honour and glory by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour Ieſu chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:6046:25"/>
               <head>Sermon. v. Of thinconueniences that are happened and dayly happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the abuſe of the holy Scryptures.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg> The holy Scriptures of them ſelues be the good giftes of got and of the holyghooſt. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles they maye be vſed of vs wel or euell / as by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it is manifeſt. For where as Gods elect ſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues of it to Gods honour / the reprobate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary wyſe ſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues of it to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour / through their owne faute a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not of the ſcriptures In ſo moch that in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of their wicked malignité it hath per chaunce done hurte in ſome wayes to the worlde / though at length / god of his infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite bounté reduceth all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d glorie. For firſt the ſcriptures a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſpecially the holy ſcriptures / haue a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>noied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who haue been dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to gather to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manie bookes / and neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſtudye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>king the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues fully learned whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue had their librarie full of bokes. Other ſome ſtudying / haue not attayned
<pb facs="tcp:6046:26"/>to imprynte the trueth that they founde in theyr mindes / and therfore haue wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it in papers / ſo that / reſting mooſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / all their learni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyſteth in their wrytinges / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d looſing them / they alſo loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe their ſcience. Which was one of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentes that cauſed Plato to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne lettres / ſayinge that before ſcripture was founde / the men were moche better learned then ſence / becauſe they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to write in theyr mindes that that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes they haue written in paper. I paſſe ouer that many haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed theyr time in the diſhonour of god / in readi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d wrytyng of thinges curious ande perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to the health. And that manie tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of Curioſyté / haue willed to ſee ſo many bookes that in the ende they remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned confuſed wythout frute. As doth the felde wheron they caſt ouermoch ſeede. And of ſome that by thoſe meanes haue loſt their wittes. But that which impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth moche more is that they thynke the true knowledge of Theologie or diuinité co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in lettres / which is vtterly falſe / becauſe they giue not true and lyuely light
<pb facs="tcp:6046:26"/>of the ſupernatural thiges that can not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be knowen of vs but by ſpyrite / reuelation / faith ſpirituall taſte / lyuely vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtanding and ſure experience. For like as the Phyloſopher without experience can haue no knowledge although he beare in minde all that is written / ande nor ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing practyſed / he muſt reſt onely in opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion grounded vppon Ariſtotle / Plato and the other Philoſophers / whiche mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth hym to beleue theyr wrytyng to be true / being neuertheles in very dede more ignoraunt then is the poore paiſaunt or huſbandman / that by labouring of the Earth / without ſekinge lettres / fyndeth the operacion of many naturall thynges / that proueth his ſcience to be ſomwat and theirs none / though well they ſtudy for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d wante experye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. So likewiſe one ſymple ydeote without learning / if he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue faith / lyuely taſte / and ſpirituall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of God / is a greater diuine then all the learned men of the worlde that be wythout ſpirite. Yea he is a diuine ande they none. For that of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall thinges he knoweth ſo moch as
<pb facs="tcp:6046:27"/>he taſteth / and exper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ateth by faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the learned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath onely a barraine / y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le colde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ade opinto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith in deſperacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / accompained of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery vice. Nowe therfore it appereth that of this errour / by thiking that true Theo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>logie or diuinite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in learning / the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re are innuaerable inconueme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces growe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and chefely that many / wanti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g letters / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not hauing tyme to ſtudie / thinking that by other wares it is impoſſible to become diuines / haue not diſpoſed them ſelues to demaunde of God with meke harte ande feruent deſyreth: lyght of the diuine thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And moreouer they haue fledde ande withdrawen them ſelues from the intelly gence or vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of the holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / as from a terrible ruyne / becauſe their wyſe learned and holy men haue perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them that no man may vnderſtand it but they onthe that are learned. Conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them that write in the vulgare ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue / as if the true diuinite depended of the Hebrue Greke or Latin lettres / or of that witte that hath well ſtudied them. Behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de nowe therfore whether this be not a
<pb facs="tcp:6046:27"/>mooſt rawe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d wicked opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / beig the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cauſe that hath moued me thus to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my natural to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that (kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wing the true Theologie to be ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry langdage and to the ſymple) our owne natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhulde not be priuate / who haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne other but the mother tongue. Ther be many that / ſtudying the holy ſcriptures without ſpirite / lyuely faith and ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall light / haue not onely not attayned the true knowledge of the bountie of God a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theyr owne propre miſeries / but the more they haue ſtudied / the more / by the drie a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d deade letter / they are become blynde of God and of them ſelues. Yea vnfaithfull / vnkind / proude arrogau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t preſumptuous contentious ande repleate of all other by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Where as the ſupernaturall true Theologie or diuinité ſtewing the great bounté of God / and declaryng in our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues our owne myſeries maketh vs faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full / thankfull / iuſte / humble / modeſt / gentle / quiet and conformable.</p>
               <p>And moreouer they be ſo blynde that not knowing theyr owne wretchednes / they not onely forbeare to hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:6046:28"/>before God / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of him hartely to demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de helpe lyght and grace / but alſo leauing praier for their ſtudie / and the ſpirite for theyr learnig / they preſume to be maſters of the others as Paule wryteth / ande ſo inflambed of theyr ſcience / haue ſtaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the worlde where as charyte edifieth.
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> And being conſequently without ſpyryte / they ſtudy and vnderſtand the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures according to their owne iudgemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / diuerſly as their wyttes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſtudie are varyable / and euery one according to hys fantaſye expoundeth them / thynkyng he hath perfectly and iuſtly conceaued them / Wherof are growen infynite ſectes ande hereſpes.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 8.</note> In ſteade of that / if they had bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d true diuines a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d had had the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of Gods gyfte / they had vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in treuth and verité / wherof followeth none other but vnion of faith both in ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte and charité.</p>
               <p>Many alſo beleuing by the ſtudie of the holy ſcriptures / to attayne true Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye and parfect knowledge of God ande conſequently the chefe felycyté poſſyble to the lyuing man / haue geuen them ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:6046:28"/>to ſtudye the ſcriptures / and walkinge by them to ioyne to the ſupreme faelicité of Gods knowledge / becauſe they wanted the ſpirite / they neyther can arryve at the true ande lyvely lyght / taſte and ſpirituall vnderſtanding of God nor yet to the true felicité. Wher of it groweth that they fall to the botome of infidelyté / in ſuche wiſe / that they beleue that there is none other light / faith or diuinité then that their bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine and deade opinion / nor other felyei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ré then that theyr myſerye / and ſo / ſeming to have attained the heigth of vertues / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have ones taſted of them / they diſprayſe them. Theſe and ſoche other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences are growen ande continual lye growe through them that knowe not how they ought to vſe the holy ſcriptures in ſoche wiſe / that by theyr default / ande not of the ſcriptures / they have perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce done hurte to the worlde. But for that we ought not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempne the letters (as many have done) but the men that knowe not to vſe them as they ſhulde be vſed to the honour of God. To whome be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d glory by our ſauiour Ieſu chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:6046:29"/>
               <head>Sermon. vj. If to bee good diuines it behoue vs to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the humaine ſciences or not.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be many that thinke it is not poſſyble to attaine the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Theologie / if fyrſt a man learne not Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer / Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lec: ica / Philoſophie and metaphiſica / Yea Scotus Thomas bonauenture ande ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che other. I confeſſe my ſelfe to haue been in that errour and therfore am nowe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to compaſſion of them that reſt blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded withall. If it were as they ſaye / we ſhulde be mooſt bounden vnto the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of thoſe ſciences / ſyns that by them we maye be good diuines / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d without the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not. And then I praye you if they happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to periſh or thoſe aucthours to be loſt ſhulde it not followe that alſo the worlde ſhuld lacke diuinité? And lykewyſe if the learned men in thoſe ſciences be onely the good diuins and conſequently Sainctes (the contrary wherof is clerely ſeen) then myght well the ſymple ande vnlearned people deſpaire of all ghooſtly health / and
<pb facs="tcp:6046:29"/>the true and neceſſarie diuinité hange vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon humaine ſciences. So by that reaſon it ſhulde behoue vs to ſaye that the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and in maner all the ſainctes / Yea and the bleſſed virgin Marie weare not good diuines / notwithſtanding that they haue taught others. No nor Chriſt neuer lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thoſe humayne ſciences / and yet was he the mooſt excellent diuine.
<note place="margin">Iohan. 7.</note> Therfore we muſt knowe that one humaine ſcience leadeth vs to clyme to an other / moche vnworthie of the name of Theologie or diuinité / but rather to be called Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſica / the which neither hath nor geveth ſo moch light of God as can ſuffyſe to our ſaluacion / being a knowledge / that by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of mannes witte / eliming the degrees of humaine reaſon / maye be attained. Where as the true ande ſupernaturall Theologie or diuinité is a ſcience of the ſpirite / a gifte ande light that by grace co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from God aboue / in ſoche wiſe / that not he that hathe the pregnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t witte / hath mooſt ſtudied and is beſt learned / is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt diuine / but he that hath faith / liuely light and vnderſtanding of God / that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb facs="tcp:6046:30"/>better and more chriſtianly.
<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe faith is a gifte of God / and the true diuinite a ſupernaturall light / not attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable or can not be attained of vs / but gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of God to hys Electe. Therfore eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſymple. Yoeote and ignoraunt of the humaine ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces / maie by the grace of god / ſodenly become a parfect diuine and chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian / as in the actes of the Apoſtles it is redde of the Eunucho.
<note place="margin">Act. 8.</note> It is poſſyble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that a ſimple olde woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye haue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the true Theologie or diuinité / then all the learned men of the worlde. For the humaine ſciences do fyll our myndes of ſmoake and pryde / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d occupie them in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wiſe (that diſtracte with Marta) they be not attentiue with Marie to receaue the knowledge of God. It is ſeen by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that rather and more lightly the ſymple haue accepted the Goſpell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the worlde. Yea where the ſymple / the ydeotes / the litle children ande the Samaritanes magnified Chriſt / the learned ſcribes and Phariſeis perſecuted him euen to the death of the croſſe. Ande whan the worlde conuerteth / ſeldome the
<pb facs="tcp:6046:30"/>learned men come to the fayth / but haue been euer the laſte. There coulde none en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tre into Sancta Sanctorum by tholde lawe / but the hygh Byſſhop. But Chriſte dying on the croſſe / hath ouerthrowen the vaile of the temple / ſo that the reſple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dent treaſures of Gods wiſdome hidde i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt<note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> are manifeſted ſo openly / that the ſymple and ydeotes / yea the publicanes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d comu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne women haue vnderſtanded them. Wherof Dauid ſpeaketh ſaying Thy wordes be open / they lyghten a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to the litleones.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.</note> That highe and diuine wiſdome is become ſo lowe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt / that euery ſymple maye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande. For that Chriſt is not come as an humaine man to teache vs letters but is diuinely a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſpiritually deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le the ſpirite / light charite and grace in the hartes of his electe / ande ſo hath he made them to vnderſtand / euen to the Children whiche magnifie hym / ſaying Bleſſed is he that is come in the name of the lorde.
<note place="margin">Math. 21.</note> And Chriſt reproued his Apoſtles when they letted the Childeren of comming to him / though nowe their be many that wil
<note place="margin">Luk. 18.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6046:31"/>not allowe the holie ſcriptures to be had in the vulgare tongue / nor redde and decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to the ſimple / as if they coulde not vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand them / nor were not bounde to knowe that which is conteined in them. And yet it is certeine / they conteine none other but proffytable and neceſſary thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the health / and that being of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyghooſt / thoſe diuine verities be in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſo expreſſed / that in what tongue ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be written / ſo it be truly declared / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with pure harte hearde and vnderſtande / they muſt nedes edifie without offendig. Chriſte thanking his father / ſayde vnto hym.
<note place="margin">Wath. 11.</note> I praiſe the (father and lorde of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen and earth) that thou haſt hidde theſe thinges from the wyſe and prudent / ande opened the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto babes / not for that they haue ſtudied / but becauſe it hath ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the.
<note place="margin">Ieremy. 3.</note> In this is fulfilled that that God promiſed by his prophet Ieremie / that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the leaſt of all they ſhulde knowe. Nowe beholde if they be blind or not / that wyll buylde the true Theologie vppon Philoſophie / and vppon the humaine ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces: where as chriſt is the true fondacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / 
<pb facs="tcp:6046:31"/>and vppon him it behoueth to buylde / not woode ſtrawe or haye / but ſyluer golde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d pretious ſtones / that is to ſaie / not the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencions of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but the onely true reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacions of God. Sainet Iohan Baptiſt / and not Ariſtotle / was the precurſor or foreru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of Chryſt. It is not poſſyble with the light of a litle burning candell to augment the great light of the Sonne a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d lykewiſe Chriſt can not be clarified by the humayne ſciences.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> He him ſelfe ſaith that he hath taken his beaulte / not of men but of his father / who ſaide vnto hi.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 13.</note> And the I haue glorified / and the I ſhall glorifie. And wilt thou then that Chryſt / which is the light of the world / ſhulde haue node of the light of Ariſtotle?
<note place="margin">Iohan. 1.</note> That theyr drye / colde and dead Theologie ſerueth to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke them proude / to preſume of them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues / to contende and to deceaue the blinde ignoraunt people with perſuading them falſely to repute them for diuines / yea a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to begile them ſelues / that albeit that they be darkenes in dede / yet they thinke them ſelues to be the light of the worlde / ande therfore humble not theyr hartes to praie
<pb facs="tcp:6046:32"/>vnto God to giue them light. I wyll not ſaye that we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſerue our ſelues of all the humaine ſciences in the honour of God / yea and of our ſynnes / in aſmoch as of them we maye take occaſyon of vertue. But I ſaye in dede that they be not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to make vs good diuines. For to that it behoueth a ſupernaturall lyght of God / with clennes and purité of harte. And this light we ought euermore to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde of God with feruent prayer / we ought alſo to ſeke the hearing of Gods worde / and with humilité to exerciſe our ſelues in ſtudying the holy ſcriptures / to the intent / that as true a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines / we maye rendre vnto God all honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie by our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6046:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
